Carlos Davila Papers
Carlos Davila Papers
1930-1957
Dávila, Carlos G., 1887-1955.
6 linear ft.
Papers of the Chilean diplomat, journalist, author. Collection includes correspondence, photographs, clippings, manuscript essays and speeches, and published addresses and essays by Dávila (1943-1954), and articles and clippings by and about Dávila.
148930
Biographical History
Carlos Davila (1887-1955) was a Chilean statesman, diplomat, editor, and writer. Davila was born in Los Angeles, Chile, and studied law at the University of Chile, Santiago. There he was president of the Students' Federation. He founded and directed the newspapers La Nacion and Los Tiempos, and the magazine Hoy.
From 1927 to 1931 he was Chile's ambassador to the United States, and in 1932 he became President of Chile. He was a member of the Interamerican Financial and Economic Advisory Committee in 1939 and 1940, and was visiting professor of International Law for the Carnegie Peace Foundation. In 1941, Davila was a recipient of the Cabot Prize awarded by Columbia University's School of Journalism for distinguished service in Inter-American relations in journalism. He was on the social and economic council of the United Nations and from 1943-1946 was on the UN Relief and Rehabilitation Administration. He received degrees of Doctor of Law Honores Causa from Columbia University and Southern California University at Los Angeles. In 1954, Davila was elected Secretary-General of OAS. He was one of the most widely read South American writers and author of the book We of the Americas.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Carlos Davila Papers consist of subject files, manuscripts, and published material (general as well as bound articles and books).
Subject files contains correspondence, photographs, clippings and related items.
Manuscripts contains manuscripts of articles, books, notes, speeches and lectures by Davila.
Published material contains addresses, articles, news clippings, pamphlets, periodicals, a report and a scrapbook. Addresses are by Davila, and by others; articles are by Davila; news clippings are about Davila, others and by Davila. Periodicals contain articles by or about Davila and are arranged first alphabetically, then chronologically.
Numbered articles by Davila contains bound articles and a bibliography. The articles are arranged chronologically and then by number.
Books consists of the collection owned by Davila; many of them are autographed.
Arrangement of the Collection
Subject files are arranged alphabetically by subject. Manuscripts and Published material are arranged alphabetically by type. Numbered articles are bound in chronological order.
Subject and Genre Headings
Journalism; Politics, government and public administration; Dávila, Carlos G., 1887-1955.; Ambassadors -- Chile.; Journalism.; Journalists -- Chile.; Pan-Americanism.; Chile -- History -- 1920-1970.; Chile -- Politics and government -- 1920-1970.; Chile -- Diplomatic and consular service -- United States.; Chile -- Foreign relations -- United States.; Latin America -- Foreign relations -- United States.; United States -- Foreign relations -- Chile.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Speeches (documents); Diplomats.; Journalists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Frances Adams Dávila, 1966.
Inventory
- Subject File
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
  - Almegro, undated (Box 1)
  - American Man, 1950-1953 (Box 1)
  - Bank deposit slip, May 6, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Cabot Award, Nov. 3, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Caricature of Davila, undated (Box 1)
  - Coffee, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Davila, Mrs. Carlos [Frances Adams], 1950-1957 (Box 1)
  - El Diario de Nueva York, Sept.-Oct. 1948 (Box 1)
  - Election to Secretaryship of OAS, June 17, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Eloy Alfaro International Foundation Cross, Jan., 1950 (Box 1)
  - Hispanic Society of America, Oct. 25, 1956 (Oversize 1)
  - "Hoy", 1933-1936 (Box 1)
  - Inter-American Financial & Economic Advisory Committee, Nov., 1939 (Box 1)
  - Inter-American Financial & Economic Advisory Committee-Davila Plan, Dec. 1934 (Box 1)
  - International Bank, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Interviews with Davila, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Joaquin Fernandez [Foreign Minister], 1943-1946 (Box 1)
  - Land, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Lotus Club, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Monroe Doctrine, 1946-1954 (Box 1)
  - OAS, 1954 (Box 1)
  - ONU [United Nations], 1952 (Box 1)
  - Oscar Fenner (Ministo), 1953 (Box 1)
  - Pan-American Week in Chicago, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Photo with note from Eduardo Rojas Jacome, Oct. 7, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Photos of Davila, undated (Box 1)
  - Portrait of Davila, undated (Box 1)
  - Promotional Material for "El Mundo Que No Fue", undated (Box 1)
  - Racquet Club, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Rotary Club of Washington, D.C., Oct. 15, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Sociedad Minera Exploradora del Tatio [Geothermic Project], 1951 (Box 1)
  - Trip to Cuba & Dominican Republic, June, 1939 (Box 2)
  - Trip to South America, 1954 (Box 2)
  - UNRA-I [United Nations Relief & Rehabilitation Administration], 1944 (Box 2)
  - UNRA-LL, 1944 (Box 2)
  - UNRA-LLL, 1944 (Box 2)
  - We of the Americas, I, 1950 (Box 2)
  - We of the Americas, II, 1949-1952 (Box 2)
  - We of the Americas, III, 1949-1954 (Box 2)
- Manuscripts
  - Articles, 1935-[1954] (Box 3)
  - Book, undated (Box 3)
  - Book: Popular History of the U.S., undated (Box 3)
  - Notes, lists, undated (Box 3)
  - Speeches, lectures, 1953-1957 (Box 3)
- Published Material
  - Addresses by Davila, 1932; 1948,; 1954 (Box 4)
  - Addresses by others, Feb. 24, 1948 (Box 4)
  - Articles by Davila, undated (Box 4)
  - News clippings about Davila, 1936-1954 (Box 4)
  - News clippings about Davila, 1941-1955 (Box 4)
  - News clippings about Davila, 1947-1954 (Box 4)
  - News clippings by Davila, 1938-1954 (Box 4)
  - Pamphlet, 1951 (Box 5)
  - Periodicals A, 1955-1956 (Box 5)
  - Periodicals C-W, 1945-1954 (Box 5)
  - Records of Consejo Nacional de Comercio 1951 Exterior, Chile (Oversize 1)
  - Report on American Republics, Oct. 1, 1944 (Box 5)
  - Resolution of OAS, Dec. 7, 1955 (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook of clippings, 1930-1932 (Oversize 1)
- Numbered Articles by Davila
  - Bibliography (Box 6)
  - Articles (#'s 1-500), 1943-1948 (Box 6)
  - Articles (#'s 541-851), 1948-1951 (Box 7)
  - Articles (#'s 852-1061), 1952-1954 (Box 8)
- Books
  * indicates the book is signed by the author
  ° indicates the book is signed by someone else
  - List of authors in Davila's Collection (Box 9)
  - Andrew, Doctor / * El Partideño (Box 9)
  - Andrew, Doctor / * Héroes Sangrantes (Box 9)
  - Arboleda, Diego Castrillion / * Sol en Tambalimbú (Box 9)
  - Arciniegas, German / Entra La Libertady El Miedo (Box 9)
  - Bello, Joaquin Edwards / °Don Eliodoro Yañez (Box 9)
  - Berman / * Hombre de Accion (Box 9)
  - Borges, Jorge Luis / La Muertey La Brujula (Box 9)
  - Bustamante I Rivero, Jose / * Tres Años de Lucha Por Luis La Democraciaenel Peru (Box 9)
  - Carbia, Romulo D. / Historia De la legenda Neyra Hispanio-American (Box 9)
  - Castro, Daltazar / * Un Hombre por el Camino (Box 9)
  - Concho, Manuel / Tradiciones Sevenenses (Box 9)
  - Contrevas, Eleazar Lopez / * El Pensamiento De Bolivar, Liberta dor (Box 9)
  - Cruz, Guillermo Feliu / * En Torno de Ricardo Palma (Box 9)
  - Cuervo, R. J. / Obras (2 parts) (Box 9)
  - Culbertson, Ely / * Total Peace (Box 9)
  - Davila, Carlos / * Nosotros, Los de las Americas, 2 copies (Box 9)
  - Davis, Harold E. / * Latin American Leaders (Box 9)
  - De Baratta, Maria / * Cuzcatgan Tipico (2 parts) (Box 9)
  - De Castro, Josúe / * Geografia Da Rome (Box 9)
  - De Cosso, Jose Llado / * Izaguirre (Box 9)
  - De Gomez, Ana Caballero / * Imagen De Niño (Box 9)
  - De LasCuevas / Biografia Del Vino de Jerez (Box 9)
  - De La Torriente, Loló / * Estudio de las Artes Plasticus en Cuba (Box 9)
  - De Quesada, Gimeney / Capitanes (Box 9)
  - De Santillan, D. A. / El Pensamiento Politico De Roosevelt (Box 9)
  - D'Halmar, Augusto / Pasion y Muerte Del-Cura-Deusto (Box 9)
  - Donnay, Maurice / °Musset y el amor (Box 9)
  - Du Maurier, Daphne / Rebeca (Una mujer inolvidable) (Box 9)
  - Eliot, Geo. Fielding / The Ramparts We Watch (Box 10)
  - Fevrava, Orestes / * Cirevon y Mirabeau (Box 10)
  - Figueras, Tomas Garcia / * Marruecos (Box 10)
  - Fuentes, Roberto Meza / * Cinco Romances de la Patria (Box 10)
  - Fuentes, Roberto Meza / * Fiesta de la Primavera (Box 10)
  - Galvey, Jose / * Estampas Limeñas (Box 10)
  - Genta, Edgardo Ubaldo / * Poesias (Box 10)
  - Gonzalez-Blanco, Pedro / Against Arciniegas (Box 10)
  - Hamilton, Carlos / Comunidad de Pueblos Hispanicos (Box 10)
  - Haring, C. H. / * The Spanish Empire in America (Box 10)
  - Hughlett, Lloyd J. / Industrialization of Latin America (Box 10)
  - Huidobro, Vicente / * La Proxima (Box 10)
  - Iglesias, Augusto / * Gabriela Mistral y El Modernismo en Chile (Box 10)
  - Iglesias, Augusto / * Entredos Siglos (Box 10)
  - Iris / * Tierra Virgin (Box 10)
  - Johnston, Eric/ * We're all in it (Box 10)
  - La Cunza, P. Manuel / * Las Doctrinas (Box 10)
  - Lagoz L., Moises / * La Caja de los Periodistas de Chile (Box 10)
  - Larrain, Sergis Fernander / * Informa (Box 10)
  - Lisboa, Rosalina Coclho / ...a seara de Caim, 2 copies (Box 10)
  - Lisboa, Rosalina Coclho / Pasos en el Camino (Box 10)
  - Lomboy, Peinaldo / Ranquil (Box 10)
  - Loucel, Maria / Ilapso (Box 10)
  - Mac-Clure, Rafael Elizalde / Los Angeles de Hollywood (Box 10)
  - Mallea, Eduardo / Historia de una Pasion Argentina (Box 11)
  - Marco, Mariategni, Jose / l Alma Matinal (Box 11)
  - Mc Bride, Geo. M. / Chile, Land and Society (Box 11)
  - Mc Connel, Burt M. / Mexico at the Bar of Public Opinion (Box 11)
  - Merrick Lectures for 1943 / Christian Bases of World Order (Box 11)
  - Mendoza, Humberto / * Socialismo (Box 11)
  - Mendoza, E. Rodriguez / El Golpe de Estado de 1924 (Box 11)
  - Molina, Abbe Don J. Ignatius / The Natural History of Chile (Box 11)
  - Molina, Abbe Don J. Ignatius / The Civil History of Chile (Box 11)
  - Nabrica, Carolina / * La Vida de Joaquim Nabuca (Box 11)
  - Naft, Stephen / * Conversion Equivalents in International Trade (Box 11)
  - Nobre, Fernando / * Academia Punlista de Letras (Box 11)
  - Nobre, Fernando / * Roma! Roma! (Box 11)
  - Norton, Henry Kittredge / °The Coming of South America (Box 11)
  - Obra Sindie al "Artesania" / °El Portesano Español os Ofrice (Box 11)
  - Occelli, Pierluigi / Pio X (Box 11)
  - Páez, Gen. Jose Antonio / Autobiografia (Box 11)
  - Pereyra, Carlos / Herman Cortes (Box 11)
  - Pierson, W. W. Jr. / * Hispanic-American History: A Syllabus (Box 11)
  - Proust, Marcel / * Sus mejores páginas (Box 11)
  - Quintanilla, Luis / A Latin American Speaks (Box 11)
  - Requena, Andres / Los Enemigos de la Tierra (Box 11)
  - Reves, Emery / The Anatomy of Peace (Box 11)
  - Rembao, Alberto / * Meditaciones Neoyorkinas (Box 11)
  - Reulet, Anibal Sanchez / * Contemporary Latin-American Policy (Box 12)
  - Reyes, Chela / * Puertas Verdes (Box 12)
  - Romero, Alberto / * La mala estrella de Perucho Gonialey (Box 12)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin D. / Por qué nos Armamos (Box 12)
  - Sacasa, Dr. Juan B. / * Como y por qué cai del poder (Box 12)
  - Salazar, Eduardo / * Derechos Del Hombre (Box 12)
  - Soule, George / Latin America in the future world (Box 12)
  - Speeches / Speeches Incident to the West, of Sec. Root to S.A. Zoe (Box 12)
  - Subercaseauz, Benjamin / Crónicas del Centenario (Box 12)
  - Varas, Atilio Macchiavello / Albas de Medianoihe (Box 12)
  - Vicuna, Alejandro / * Abelardo (Box 12)
  - Vicuna, Alejandro / * Ciceron (Box 12)
  - Vicuna, Alejandro / * Horacio (Box 12)
  - Vicuna, Alejandro / * Imes de Suarez (Box 12)
  - Vicuna, Alejandro / * Pablo de Tarp (Box 12)
  - Vicuna, Alejandro / Yo, El Jordan (Box 12)
  - Townsend, Francis E. / Quisqueya (Box 12)
  - Ziff, William B. / * Two Worlds (Box 12)